My goal for the next few segments is to
show you that if we use a secure PRG We'll
下面几节我将说明，如果我们使用一个安全的PRG
get a secure stream cipher. The first thing
we have to do is define is, what does it
我们将得到一个安全的流密码。首先我们必须要定义
mean for a stream cipher to be secure? So
whenever we define security we always
流密码的安全性是指什么。无论何时我们定义安全
define it in terms of what can the
attacker do? And what is the attacker
我们总是根据攻击者能干什么或者企图干什么来定义
trying to do? In the context of
stream ciphers remember these are only used
记住在流密码的情况下，只使用一次性密钥
with a onetime key, and as a result the
most the attacker is ever going to see is
因此攻击者最多只看到
just one cypher text encrypted using the
key that we're using. And so we're gonna
当前我们使用的密钥加密后的密文
limit the attacker's ability to basically
obtain just one cypher text. And in
那么我们将要限制攻击者只能获得一个密文
fact later on we're going to allow the
attacker to do much, much, much more, but
事实上稍后我们将允许攻击者做更多事情
for now we're just gonna give him one
cypher text. And we wanted to find,
但现在我们只给他一个密文  我们想探究
what does it mean for the cypher to
be secure? So the first definition that
密码的安全性到底指什么？那么首先想到的第一个定义
comes to mind is basically to say, well
maybe we wanna require that the attacker
就是我们会要求攻击者
can't actually recover the secret key.
Okay so given ciphertext you
无法还原密钥。给定密文
shouldn't be able to recover the secretkey.
But that's a terrible definition
你应该是无法还原密钥的。但这是一个糟糕的定义
because think about the falling brilliant
cipher but the way we encrypt the
因为想想这个聪明但失败了的密码
message using a key K is basically
we just output the message. Okay this
我们使用密钥K加密消息的方式只是输出消息
is a brilliant cipher yeah of course it
doesn't do anything given a message just
这是一个聪明的密码，当然，它没有做任何事情
output a message as the cipher text.
This is not a particularly good encryption
只是输出明文当做密文。这并不是一个特别好的加密机制
scheme; however, given the cipher text,
mainly the message the poor attacker
然而给定密文，弱攻击者无法还原密钥
cannot recover the key because he doesn't
know what the key is. And so as a result
因为他不知道密钥
this cipher which clearly is insecure,
would be considered secure under this
因此这个明显不安全的密码，在这个安全要求下被认为是安全的
requirement for security. So this
definition will be no good. Okay so it's
所以这个定义不好
recovering the secret key is the wrong way
to define security. So the next thing we
所以从还原密钥的角度定义安全是错误的
can kinda attempt is basically just say,
well maybe the attacker doesn't care about
下一步我们要尝试的是，或许攻击者并不在意密钥
the secret key, what he really cares about
are the plain text. So maybe it should be
他真正在乎的是明文
hard for the attacker to recover the
entire plain text. But even that doesn't
因此对攻击者来说还原整个明文可能比较困难
work because let's think about the
following encryption scheme. So suppose
但而这样也没有用。想一想下面的加密机制
what this encryption scheme does is it
takes two messages, so I'm gonna use two
假设这个加密机制是取两个信息
lines to denote concatenation of two
messages M0 line, line M1 means
我用双竖线来表示两个信息的串联，M0||M1表示M0串上M1
concatenate M0 and M1. And imagine
what the scheme does is really it outputs
这个加密机制输出M0的明文
M0 in the clear and concatenate to
that the encryption of M1. Perhaps even
串上M1的加密后的密文
using the One Time Pad okay? And
so here the attacker is gonna be given one
可能使用了一次一密，怎么样?这里攻击者得到了密文
cipher text. And his goal would be to
recover the entire plain texts. But the
他的目标是还原整个明文
poor attacker can't do that because here
maybe we've encrypted M1 using the One
但弱攻击者做不到，因为这里我们可以用一次一密加密M1
Time Pad so the attacker can't
actually recover M1 because we know the
这样攻击者无法还原M1
One Time Pad is secure given just
one cipher text. So this construction
因为只给一个密文的话，一次一密是安全的
would satisfy the definition but
unfortunately clearly this is not a secure
所以这个结构会符合这个定义。但不幸的是，这明显不是安全的加密机制
encryption scheme because we just leaked
half of the plain text. M0 is
因为我们泄露了一半的明文内容
completely available to the attacker so
even though he can't recover all of the
攻击者完全知道M0，即使他无法完全还原出所有的明文
plain text he might be able to recover
most of the plain text, and that's clearly
他也能还原出大部分明文了，这明显是不安全的
unsecured. So of course we already know
the solution to this and we talked about
我们已经知道了这个问题的解决方案
Shanon definition of security perfect
secrecy where Shannon's idea was that in
我们讨论过香农对完善保密性的定义
fact when the attacker intercepts a cipher
text he should learn absolutely no
香农的想法是，当攻击者截获密文时
information about the plain texts. He
shouldn't even learn one bit about the
他得不到关于明文的任何信息，甚至得不到明文一个比特的信息
plain text or even he shouldn't learn, he
shouldn't even be able to predict a little
预测不到明文一个比特的信息
bit about a bid of the plain text.
Absolutely no information about the plain text.
完全没有关于明文的任何信息
So let's recall very briefly
Shannon's concept of perfect secrecy
我们简要回顾一下香农的完善保密性的概念
basically we said that you know given a
cipher We said the cipher has perfect
我们说一个密码具备完善保密性
secrecy if given two messages of the same
length it so happens that the distribution
只有当给定两个长度相同的消息
of cipher texts. Yet if we pick a random
key and we look into distribution of
和随机选择的一个密钥
cipher texts we encrypt M0 we get
exactly the same distribution as when we
M0的密文与M1的密文具有完全相同的分布时成立
encrypt M1. The intuition here was that if
the advisory observes the cipher texts
直观地看，如果敌手观察密文
then he doesn't know whether it came from
the distribution the result of encrypting
那么他无法得知密文的分布
M0 or it came from the distribution as
the result of encrypting M1. And as a
是加密M0的结果还是加密M1的结果
result he can't tell whether we encrypted
M0 or M1. And that's true for all
于是他无法判断我们加密的是M0还是M1
messages of the same length and as a
result a poor attacker doesn't really know
这一点对所有等长的消息都成立。弱攻击者无法得知
what message was encrypted. Of course we
already said that this definition is too
我们加密的是什么消息。当然从某种意义上
strong in the sense that it requires
really long keys if cipher has short
这个定义太强了，它需要很长的密钥
keys can't possibly satisfy this
definition in a particular stream ciphers
如果密钥太短，不可能满足这一定义
can satisfy this definition. Okay so let's
try to weaken the definition a little bit
特别地，流密码不能满足这个定义。好的，我们试图削弱这个定义
and let's think to the previous segment,
and we can say that instead of requiring
想一想上节的内容
the two distributions to be absolutely
identical what we can require is, is that
我们不是要求两个分布绝对相同
two distributions just be computationally
indistinguishable. In other words a poor,
而是要求两个分布只在计算上不可区分
efficient attacker cannot distinguish the
two distributions even though the
换句话说，高效的弱攻击者无法区分两个分布
distributions might be very, very, very
different. That just given a sample for
即使这两个分布非常不同。仅仅给一个分布的样本
one distribution and a sample for another
distribution the attacker can't tell which
和另一分布的样本，攻击者无法区分
distribution he was given a sample from.
It turns out this definition is actually
他得到的样本来自哪一个分布。这个定义基本上是正确的
almost right, but it's still a little too
strong, that still cannot be satisfied, so
但它还是有点太强了，仍然无法满足
we have to add one more constraint, and
that is that instead of saying that this
所以我们不得不再加一条限制，那就是不要求这个定义
definition should have hold for all M0 and M1. It is to hold for only pairs M0 M1
对所有的和M0和M1都成立，而只要求对攻击者
that the attackers could
actually exhibit. Okay so this actually
实际能建立的一对明文（M0，M1）成立
leads us to the definition of semantics
security. And so, again this is semantics
好，那么我们来定义语义安全
security for one time key in other words
when the attacker is only given one cipher
这里指一次性密钥的语义安全。换句话说，这是当攻击者只得到一个密文的情况
text. And so the way we define semantic
security is by defining two experiments,
我们通过定义两个实验来定义语义安全
okay we'll define experiment 0 and
experiment 1. And more generally we will
分别是实验0和实验1
think of these as experiments parentheses
B, where B can be zero or one. Okay so the
更一般地，我们可以把这些实验当做实验B，B可以是0或1
way the experiment is defined is as
follows, we have an adversary that's
所以实验如下定义：有一敌手A试图攻破加密系统
trying to break the system. An adversary
A, that's kinda the analog of statistical
，就像伪随机数发生器的统计测试那样
tests in the world of pseudo random
generators. And then the challenger does
然后挑战者这样做
the following, so really we have two
challengers, but the challengers are so
事实上我们有两个挑战者
similar that we can just describe them as
a single challenger that in one case takes
但这两个挑战者很相似，所以我们可以把他们想象成一个挑战者
his inputs bits set to zero, and the other
case takes his inputs bits set to
在一种情况下输入比特为0，在另一种情况下输入比特为1
one. And let me show you what these
challengers do. The first thing the
我们来看这些挑战者做了什么
challenger is gonna do is it's gonna pick
a random key and then the adversary
首先，挑战者选取一个随机密钥
basically is going to output two messages
M0 and M1. Okay so this is an explicit
然后敌手输出两个消息M0和M1
pair of messages that the attacker wants
to be challenged on and as usual we're not
那么这是攻击者希望被挑战的一对信息
trying to hide the length of the messages,
we require that the messages be equal
与往常一样，我们不试图隐藏信息长度，我们要求两个信息的长度一致
length. And then the challenger basically
will output either the encryption of M0
然后挑战者输出M0的加密结果或M1的加密结果
or the encryption of M1, okay so in
experiment 0 the challenger will output
在实验0里挑战者会输出M0的加密
the encryption of M0. In experiment 1 the challenger will output the encryption
在实验1里挑战者会输出M1的加密
of M1. Okay so that the difference between
the two experiments. And then the
这就是两个实验之间的差别
adversary is trying to guess basically
whether he was given the encryption of M0
然后敌手试图猜测，他得到的是M0的加密
or given the encryption of M1. Okay so
here's a little bit of notation let's
还是M1的加密。这里引入一些记号
define the events Wb to be the events that
an experiment B the adversary output one.
我们定义事件Wb为在实验B中敌手输出1的所有事件
Okay so that is just an event that
basically in experiment zero W0 means that
事件W0意思是在实验0中敌手输出1
the adversary output one and in experiment
one W1 means the adversary output one. And
W1意思是在实验1中输出1
now we can define the advantage of this
adversary, basically to say that this is
现在我们可以定义敌手的优势
called the semantics security advantage of
the adversary A against the scheme E,
即敌手A对加密机制E的语义安全的优势
to be the difference of the probability of
these two events. In other words we are
定义为两个事件概率的差
looking at whether the adversary behaves
differently when he was given the
换句话说，我们关注的是敌手得到M0的加密和M1的加密时
encryption of M0 from when he was given
the encryption of M1. And I wanna make
他的行为有何不同
sure this is clear so I'm gonna say it one
more time. So in experiment zero he was
为确保这点讲清楚我再说一遍
given the encryption of M0 and in
experiment one he was given the encryption
在实验0中给敌手M0的加密，在实验1中给他M1的加密
of M1. Now we're just interested in
whether the adversary output 1 or not.
现在我们感兴趣的是敌手是否输出1
... In these experiments. If in both
experiments the adversary output 1 with
如果两个实验中敌手以同样的概率输出1
the same probability that means the
adversary wasn't able to distinguish the
就意味着敌手无法区分两个实验
two experiments. Experiments zero
basically looks to the adversary the same
对敌手而言实验0与实验1相同
as experiment one because in both cases
upload one with the same probability.
因为两种情况都以同样概率输出1
However if the adversary is able to output
1 in one experiment with significantly
然而如果敌手在两个实验中输出1的概率差别很大
different probability than in the other
experiment, then the adversary was
那么敌手是可以区分两个实验的
actually able to distinguish the two
experiments. Okay so... To say this more
更正式地说
formally, essentially the advantage again
because it's the difference of two
就用优势来表示。因为优势是两概率之差，值在0到1之间
probabilities the advantage is a number
between zero and one. If the advantage is
如果优势接近0
close to zero that means that the
adversary was not able to distinguish
意味着敌手无法区分实验0和1
experiment zero from experiment one.
However if the advantage is close to one,
但如果优势接近1
that means the adversary was very well
able to distinguish experiment zero from
意味着敌手能很好地区分实验0和1
experiment one and that really means that
he was able to distinguish an encryption
也就是他能很好地区分M0和M1的加密
of M0 from an encryption of M1, okay?So that's out definition. Actually
那么这就是我们的定义
that is just the definition of the
advantage and the definition is just what
实际上这就是优势的定义
you would expect basically we'll say that
a symmetric encryption scheme is
我们说，一个对称加密机制
semantically secure if for all efficient
adversaries here I'll put these in quotes
是语义安全的，如果对于所有有效的敌手
这里要加上双引号
again, "For all efficient adversaries the
advantage is negligible." In other words,
“对所有有效敌手，优势可忽略”
no efficient adversary can distinguish the
encryption of M0 from the encryption
换句话说，没有有效敌手可以区分M0和M1的加密
of M1 and basically this is what it
says repeatedly that for these two
这一定义反复在说
messages that the adversary was able to
exhibit he wasn't able to distinguish
对这两个给定的明文
敌手无法区分这两种分布
these two distributions. Now I want to
show you this, this is actually a very
这是一个优雅的定义
elegant definition. It might not seem so
right away, but I want to show you some
可能不是很直观，但我想说明这个定义的一些含义
implications of this definition and you'll
see exactly why the definition is the way
然后你们会清楚地看到为何这么定义
it is. Okay so let's look at some
examples. So the first example is suppose
好的，我们来看一些例子。第一个例子
we have a broken encryption scheme, in
other words suppose we have an adversary A
假设我们有一个被破解的加密机制。也就是说，我们有一个敌手A
that somehow given the cipher text he is
always able to deduce the least
给定密文，他总能推断出明文的最低有效位
significant bit of the plain text. Okay so
given the encryption of M0, this adversary
那么给定明文M0的加密
is able to deduce the least significant
bit of M0. So that is a terrible
敌手可以推断出M0的最低有效位
encryption scheme because it basically
leaks the least significant bit of the
那么这是个糟糕的加密机制
plain text just given the cipher text. So
I want to show you that this scheme is
因为给定密文的话，它泄露了明文的最低位
therefore semantically secure so that kind
of shows that if a system is semantically
如果加密系统是语义安全的话
secure than there is no attacker of this
type. Okay so let's see why is the system
是不会有这样的攻击者的
not semantically secure well so what we
are gonna do is we're gonna basically use
我们看为什么这个系统不是语义安全的。我们要做的就是利用这个敌手
our adversary who is able to learn our
most insignificant bits, we're going to
他可以获得我们的有效位
use him to break semantic security so
we're going to use him to distinguish
我们就利用他来破坏语义安全，利用他来区分
experiment zero from experiment one Okay
so here is what we are going to do. We are
实验0和实验1。这就是我们要做的
algorithm B, we are going to be algorithm
B and this algorithm B is going to use
我们是算法B，算法B里面将会用到算法A
algorithm A in its belly. Okay so the
first thing that is going to happen is of
所以在一开始
course the challenger is going to choose a
random key. The first thing that is going
挑战者选择一个随机密钥
to happen is that we need to output two
messages. The messages that we are going
我们首先需要输出两个消息
to output basically are going to have
differently significant bits. So one
具有不同的有效位
message is going to end with zero and one
message is going to end with one. Now what
一个消息以0结尾，一个消息以1结尾
is the challenger going to do? The
challenger is going to give us the
现在挑战者要干什么？他将为我们
encryption of either M0 or M1,
depending on whether in experiment 0 or
加密M0或M1，这取决于是实验0还是1
in experiment 1. And then we just
forward this cipher text to the adversary
然后我们就把得到的密文给敌手
okay so the adversary A. Now what is the
property of adversary A? Given the cipher
现在敌手A有什么特性？
text, adversary A can tell us what the
least significant bits of the plain text is.
给定密文，敌手A可以算出明文的最低有效位
In other words the adversary is going
to output the least significant bits of M0 or M1
换句话说，敌手会输出M0或M1的最低位
but low and behold that's
basically the bit B. And then we're just
现在注意到那是位B
going to output that as our guest so let?s
call this thing B prime Okay so now this
然后把它当作我们的猜测输出，记为B'
describes the semantic security adversary.
And now you tell me what is the semantic
这就是语义安全敌手的描述。现在你们说
security advantage of this adversary? Well
so let's see. In experiment zero, what is
这个敌手语义安全的优势是多少？我们看一下，在实验0中
the probability that adversary B outputs
one? Well in experiment zero it is always
敌手B输出1的概率是多少？在实验0中
given the encryption of M zero and
therefore adversary A is always output the
总是得到M0的加密，因此敌手A
least significant bit of M zero which
always happens to be zero. In experiment
总是输出M0的最低位0
zero, B always outputs zero. So the
probability that outputs one is zero.
在实验0中，B总是输出0，所以输出1的概率是0
However in experiment one, we're given the
encryption of M1. So how likely is
但在实验1中，我们得到M1的加密
adversary B to output one in experiment
one well it always outputs one, again by
那么敌手B在实验1中输出1的概率是多少？
the properties of algorithm A and
therefore the advantage basically is one.
根据算法A的性质，概率总是1，因此优势为1
So this is a huge advantage, it's as big
as it's gonna get. Which means that this
所以这是个很大的优势，取到了最大值
adversary completely broke the system.
Okay so we consider, so under semantic
这意味着敌手完全破解了这个系统。那么我们认为，在语义安全下
security basically just deducing the least
significant bits is enough to completely
能推导出最低位就足以完全破解系统
break the system under a semantic security
definition. Okay, now the interesting
这是根据语义安全的定义来的
thing here of course is that this is not
just about the least significant bit, in
有趣的是，不仅仅是最低位
fact of the message for
example the most significant bit, you know
事实上，例如消息的最有效高位即第七位
bit number seven Maybe the XOR of all the bits in the message and so on
或者明文所有位的异或，等等
and so forth any kind of information, any
bit about the plain text they can be
任何一种信息，明文的任一位
learned basically would mean that the
system is not semantically secure. So
如果它们能被获得，都意味着系统不是语义安全的
basically all the adversary would have to
do would be to come up with two messages
敌手要做的就是用两个消息M0和M1
M0 and M1 such that under one thing that
they learned it's the value zero and then
一种情况下能够得到值0，另一种能得到值1
the other thing, the value, is one. So for
example if A was able to learn the XOR
例如如果A知道明文所有位的异或
bits of the message then M0
and M1 would just have different
M0和M1所有位的异或刚好不同
XOR for all the bits of their
messages and then this adversary A would
这样敌手A就可以
also be sufficient to break semantic
security. Okay so, basically for cipher
破解语义安全了
is semantically secure then no
bit of information is revealed to an
对于语义安全的密码，任一有效敌手
efficient adversary. Okay so this is
exactly a concept of perfect secrecy only
都无法得知明文一个比特的信息。这就是完善保密性的概念
applied just efficient adversaries
rather than all adversaries. So the next
只针对有效的敌手，而不是所有的敌手
thing I wanna show you is that in fact the
one time pad in fact is
下面我想说的是，事实上
semantically secure, they better be
semantically secure because it's in fact,
一次一密是语义安全的，它比语义安全还要好
it's more than that it's perfectly secure.
So let's see why that's true. Well so
因为它不仅仅是完善保密的。那么我们来看看这是为什么
again it's one of these experiments, so
suppose we have an adversary that claims
再来看看这个实验，设想我们有一敌手
to break semantic security of the one time
pad. The first the adversary is gonna do
他声称破解了一次一密的语义安全
is he's gonna output two messages M0
and M1 of the same length.
首先敌手输出两个等长明文M0和M1
Now what does he get back as a challenge? As a
challenge, he gets either the encryption
作为挑战他能得到什么呢？
of M0 or the encryption of M1 under
the one time pad.
他能得到用一次一密加密的M0或M1
And he's trying to distinguish between those two possible
cipher texts that he gets, right?
他试图区分这两个可能的密文
In experiment zero, he gets the encryption of
M0 and in experiment one, he gets the
在实验0中，他获得了M0的加密，在实验1中，他获得了M1的加密
encryption of M1. Well so let me ask
you, so what is the advantage of adversary
那么敌手对一次一密的优势是多少？
A against the one time patent? So I
remember that the property of the ones I
一次一密的性质是
had is that, that K, XOR M0 is
distributed identically to K, XOR M1.
K异或M0的分布和K异或M1的分布是一样的
In other words, these distributions are
absolutely identical distribution,
也就是说，这些分布是完全相同的分布
distributions, identical. This is a
property of XOR. If we XOR the random pad
这是异或的性质。如果我们把随机密钥K与任何消息异或
K with anything, either M0 or M1,
we get uniform distribution. So in both
不管是M0还是M1，我们都得到均匀分布
cases, algorithm A is given as in input
exactly the same distribution. Maybe the
所以在两种情况下，算法A的输入都是是严格的同分布
uniform distribution on cipher texts. And
therefore it's gonna behave exactly the
密文都是均匀分布。所以两种情况下敌手表现相同
same in both cases because it was given
the exact distribution as input. And as a
因为它得到了相同的分布作为输入
result, its advantage is zero, which means
that the onetime pad is semantically
因此它的优势是0，即一次一密是语义安全的
secure. Now the interesting thing here is
not only is it semantically secure, it's
有趣的是它不仅是语义安全的
semantically secure for all adversaries.
We don't even have to restrict the
它对任何敌手都是语义安全的，我们甚至不必限制
adversaries to be efficient. No adversary,
doesn't matter how smart you are, no
敌手是有效的，无论多聪明的敌手
adversary will be able to distinguish K XOR M0 from K XOR M1 because the two
都无法区分K异或M0和K异或M1
distributions are identical. Okay, so the
one time pad is semantically secure. Okay,
因为它们同分布。所以一次性密码本是语义安全的
so that completes our definition of
semantic security so the next thing we're
这就完善了语义安全的定义
going to do is prove to the secure PRG,
in fact implies that the stream cipher is
下面我们要证明，安全的PRG意味着流密码
semantically secure.
是语义安全的